### **Amanda French**

amanda@amandafrench.net | amandafrench.net | @amandafrench | 720-530-7515

# **Summary**

I am an experienced and successful digital project director, community manager, administrator, supervisor, grant writer, and web developer; a popular teacher of digital skills; a knowledgeable expert in digital humanities, scholarly communication, Open Access, Agile software development processes, and digital cultural heritage; and, all in all, a fun and effective colleague.

## Experience

Director, Resilient Networks for Inclusive Digital Humanities, George Washington University Libraries and Academic Innovation, February 2017-March 2019. -Managed a project to create a cross-institutional digital humanities support network and training program. Administered \$500,000 Andrew W. Mellon Foundation grant to George Washington University Libraries and Academic Innovation, including sub-awards to Davidson College, Prairie View A&M University, and Rice University. Organized team meetings and unconferences; oversaw programs to award funds; developed project website; coordinated digital curriculum development.

# Director, Digital Research Services, University Libraries, Virginia Tech, 2015-2017. -

- Managed the institutional repository, VTechWorks; implemented Scrum; managed the integration of Symplectic Elements with DSpace; worked to build digital humanities infrastructure in the library; oversaw the creation of digital imaging and preservation services; led and coordinated workshops, playdates, transcribathons, and other events; supervised 6-8 librarians, developers, staff members, and students; developed and managed annual department budgets up to \$90,000; evaluated software and hardware purchases; wrote job descriptions and hired for several positions at various levels; contributed to several internal grant proposals; co-wrote NEH grant proposal with Dr. Ed Gitre for the crowdsourced transcription project "The American Soldier," participated in the IT Governance group, the Library Council, the Web Advisory Group, the Open Knowledge Committee; wrote and published articles and gave presentations; and participated in national and international initiatives such as SHared Acccess to REsearch (SHARE) and the Digital Library Federation (DLF) Program Committee.

**Grant Writer (2014-2015)** — Coordinated the efforts of the Modern Language Association

and three partner organizations to draft, revise, and submit a successful \$1.9 million grant proposal to the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation: "Connected Academics: Preparing Doctoral Students of Language and Literature for a Variety of Careers." Helped the CUNY Graduate Center write grant proposals to the Sloan Foundation and the NEH related to creating an institutional repository for CUNY and creating a teaching-centric "Commons in a Box" system.

**THATCamp Coordinator / Research Assistant Professor, Roy Rosenzweig Center** for History and New Media, George Mason University (2010-2014) — Managed influential digital humanities scholarly communication project. Built and managed policy, technical, and administrative infrastructure for THATCamp (The Humanities and Technology Camp), an international scholarly unconference network of more than 200 events; wrote grant reports and grant proposals for two \$250,000 awards and raised additional funds; directed a comprehensive website redevelopment and redesign process with two subcontractors; supervised two part-time assistants; administered three fellowship programs that awarded more than 130 fellowships, including creating a review process and appointing two dozen scholars as fellowship reviewers; traveled to more than thirty unconferences in the U.S. and Europe to teach digital skills workshops and help run the events; wrote support and policy documents for unconference website; supported unconference organizers and representatives of at least a dozen scholarly associations; thrice organized a popular annual digital humanities event (THATCamp CHNM) attended by about 150 people each year; and promoted THATCamp in social media and at scholarly meetings.

Digital Curriculum Specialist / Assistant Research Scholar, Archives and Public History M.A. Program, New York University (2008-2010) — Revised curriculum of Archives and Public History M.A. program to incorporate digital skills, created and taught workshops and classes in subjects such as Web 2.0, HTML, and CSS; obtained server space for student projects; installed and administered Omeka archive and exhibit system; designed and co-taught the course "Creating Digital History"; helped arrange digital internships for graduate students; built project websites in Drupal and WordPress; tracked and reported on website traffic.

Visiting Assistant Professor, North Carolina State University (2006-2007) — Created and taught technology-rich courses, including English graduate courses (Bibliography and Methodology, Victorian Poetry); English undergraduate courses (History of English Literature II, The Victorian Period); and Honors seminars (Advanced Academic Research, Literary Scandals and Controversies).

the North Carolina Sociolinguistic Archive and Analysis Project (NCSLAAP); conducted usability tests on the Libraries' website; co-taught an undergraduate honors seminar on academic research skills and issues; served on library committees including the Website Redesign Steering Committee; wrote major report on web traffic using Urchin web analytics.

#### Education

Ph.D., English, U of Virginia, August 2004.

M.A., English, concentration in Women's Studies, U of Virginia, January 1995.

B.A., English, cum laude English, cum laude Arts and Sciences, U of Colorado at Boulder, May 1992.

## **Project Experience**

Grant Co-Writer and Co-Principal Investigator (converted to Advisory Board), NEH Humanities Collections and Reference Resources project "The American Soldier: A Collaborative Digital Archive," since August 2016.

Grant Co-Writer and Community Manager, NEH Chairman's Grant project Frankenreads, since November 2016.

Project Lead, "Steepletop Library: The Books of Edna St. Vincent Millay," since 2011.

Facilitator, Arthur Vining Davis Digital Humanities Summer Faculty Workshop, Northwestern University, August 2013, August 2014.

Instructor, Omeka workshops: University of Colorado at Boulder, July 2014; Muhlenberg College, October 2013; many THATCamps. "Intro to Omeka" lesson plan, Editors' Choice, <u>Digital Humanities Now</u>, November 2013.

Participant or Co-Facilitator, Book Sprints: LabCraft, Stratford-upon-Avon, UK, May 2014; Book Sprint on Book Sprints, Berlin, Germany, May 2014; Public Library of Science, San Francisco, CA, February 2014; Google Doc Camp, Mountain View, CA, October 2013.

Principal Investigator, Andrew W. Mellon Foundation funded project, "Sustaining Digital Humanities Training Through THATCamp," 2013-2014.

#### Selected Invited Talks

Panel remarks, "Libraries, the Digital Humanities, and Organizational Change," Dartmouth

College Library, October 2014.

"On Projects, and THATCamp," keynote, Digital Humanities Project Directors Meeting, National Endowment for the Humanities, October 2013. (Event canceled due to government shutdown.)

"Why Not Invent Human Intercourse?": Scholarly Conversations at THATCamp (The Humanities and Technology Camp)," Freedman Center Colloquium: Exploring Collaboration in Digital Scholarship, Case Western University, Cleveland, OH, April 2013.

"Visual Arguments in the Digital Humanities," Visualizing the Digital: Design, Ideas, and Platforms, panel, Digital Pragmata, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, VA, March 2013.

Panel remarks, "New Roles, New Expertise, New Hiring Practices," ARL-ACRL Human Resources Symposium, Washington, DC, November 2012.

"Alexandria is a Port: The Digital Library in Physical Space," response to John Palfrey at the Fredric M. Miller Memorial Lecture, Philadelphia, PA, May 2012.

"Aubade: The Soul and Body of a Library," Digital Public Library of America plenary meeting, Washington, DC, October 2011.

"Imagine a National Digital Library: I Wonder If We Can," keynote, Electronic Resources and Libraries, Austin, TX, March 2011.

Co-host of Digital Campus podcast, http://digitalcampus.tv, 2010-2015.

#### Selected Other Talks

Co-presenter, "Resilient Networks for Inclusive Digital Humanities," Digital Humanities 2017, Montréal, Canada, August 2017.

Panel remarks, Our Gadgets, Ourselves: Virtues, Vices and These New Devices, Transduction Lecture Series, Charlottesville, VA, April 2014.

"Millay and Her Books," Things My Computer Taught Me About Poems (panel organizer), special session, Modern Language Association Annual Convention, Chicago, IL, January 2014.

Panel remarks, "Global MOOCs," GABFest MOOCs, Charlottesville, VA, November 2013.

"Introduction to Omeka," Two Tools for Student-Generated Digital Projects: WordPress and Omeka in the Classroom, special session, Modern Language Association Annual

Convention, Boston, MA, January 2013.

Panel remarks, Large Digital Libraries: Beyond Google Books, special session, Modern Language Association Annual Convention, Los Angeles, CA, January 2012.

"Your Twitter Followers and Facebook Friends Won't Read Your Peer-Reviewed Article If They Have to Pay For It, and Neither Will Strangers," The Open Professoriat on the Social Web, special session, Modern Language Association Annual Convention, Los Angeles, CA, January 2011.

# **Selected Writings**

French, Amanda et al., "How We Went from Worst Practices to Best Practices, and Became Happier in the Process," <u>code4lib Journal</u> 32, 2016-04-25.

French, Amanda. "My Scandalous Future in Libraries." Re:Thinking Blog, Council on Library and Information Resources, 2015-07-07.

Fitzpatrick, Kathleen et al., "Voices: Twitter at Conferences," edited contribution in <u>Hacking the Academy: A Book Crowdsourced in One Week</u>, eds. Dan Cohen and Tom Scheinfeldt, University of Michigan Press, 2013.

"Knowledge Under Pressure," review of <u>Too Big to Know</u> by David Weinberger, <u>Journal of Interactive Technology & Pedagogy</u> September 2012.

Watson, Amanda, Amanda French, Patricia Hswe, and Christa Williford, "Of Hybrarians, Scholar-Librarians, Academic Refugees, and Feral Professionals," in <u>#Alt-Academy:</u>
<u>Alternate Academic Careers for Humanities Scholars</u>, ed. Bethany Nowviskie,
MediaCommons 2011.

See also blog posts at http://amandafrench.net.

#### **Professional Service**

Advisory Board, CORE, 2015-present.

Editorial Board, The Journal of Interactive Technology and Pedagogy, 2012-present.

Editorial Board, Archive, 2011-present.

Outreach Working Group, National Digital Stewardship Alliance, 2011-2013.

Advisory Board, Drexel University Legacy Center Digital History Toolkit, 2010-present.

Digital Library Federation Fall Forum program committee, 2010.

Reviewer, Digital Humanities conference, 2009-present.

Reviewer, National Endowment for the Humanities, Office of Digital Humanities, 2009.

## Languages and Skills

Spoken and written French (translation capability); some German, Spanish, Italian.

PHP, (X)HTML, CSS; TEI, SGML, XML.

UNIX, Linux, Mac, Windows; emacs, nano, vim, Markdown; git, GitHub.

WordPress, Omeka, Scalar, DSpace, Open Journal Systems, some Drupal.

Adobe Creative Cloud (Photoshop, Illustrator), Audacity, GarageBand, iMovie, Peak, Morae, Camstudio.

Blackboard, Moodle, Sakai, Zotero, EndNote, WebEx, blogs, wikis, podcasts, research databases.

Microsoft Office (Word, Excel, PowerPoint), Open Office, iLife.

# **Professional Memberships**

Modern Language Association

Association for Computers and the Humanities